Guide to the William J. Baumol Papers, 1928-2013 and undated RL.00092
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Professional Service, 1942-2010 and undated
  - Conferences, Consulting, and Organizations, 1942-2010 and undated; 1
    - Conference on Cultural Economics, 1985 (Box 18)
      Includes files for conference presentation by Hilda and William Baumol
    - Consultants in Industry Economics, 1993 (Box 59)
      Includes sample letterhead and forms from consulting company
    - Consulting Miscellaneous, 1988-1998 (Box 59)
      Includes files and correspondence related to various unsorted consulting activities
    - Cost Disease Talk, 1996 (Box 63)
      Includes materials for presentation on cost disease
    - Cost Indices, 1981 (Box 15)
      Includes materials related to consulting for Rochester Telephone
    - Council for Financial Aid and Education, undated (Box 59)
    - Department of Agriculture, 1942-1952; 2 folders (Box 15)
      Includes draft consulting reports and related materials
    - Department of Health and Human Services, 1981; 3 folders (Box 15)
      Includes materials related to consulting on retirement systems
    - Department of the US Navy, 1958-1963 (Box 15)
      Includes materials related to consulting for the navy
    - Dinner in Honor of WJB EPS/ASSA meetings Chicago, 2007 (Box 63)
      Includes materials for a dinner hosted by Economists for Peace and Security in Chicago to honor Baumol
    - Draft grant proposal, 1983-1986; 13 text files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0002, Disk RL00092-FL5-0107)
    - Dublin Talk - Market Incentives for Coordinated Pro-Social Voluntarism in Innovation and Environmental Protection, 1999 (Box 63)
      Includes materials for talk given at conference in Dublin
    - Eastern Economic Association, 1977-1985; 3 folders (Box 63)
      Includes documents related to service as association President
    - Economic Policy Council, New Jersey, 1970-1974 (Box 15)
      Includes materials for service on the council
    - ECPR Price Discrimination Talk, undated (Box 63)
      Includes presentation materials
    - Education Talk, undated (Box 63)
      Includes notes for lecture
    - Entrepreneurship and Education Project Progress Reports, 2004 (Box 63)
    - Entrepreneurship Theory, undated (Box 40)
      Includes notes for a talk
    - Entrepreneurship, Innovation, and the Growth Mechanism of the Free-Market Economies, 2003; 2 folders (Box 63)
      Includes materials for conference organizing
    - Entrepreneurship, Innovation, and the Growth Mechanism of the Free-Market Economies, 2003-2004; 3 folders (Box 64)
    - Exhibition in Utrecht, 2007 (Box 64)
      Includes materials for an art exhibition
    - First American Congress of Theatre, 1974 (Box 18)
      Includes files for conference presentation
    - Fishman-Davidson Center for the Study of the Service Sector, 1987-1988 (Box 64)
      Includes materials for grant application
    - Ford Foundation, 1985 (Box 64)
      Includes materials for grant application researching international security
    - Ford Foundation: Performing Arts, 1982 (Box 18)
      Includes draft proposal for project to study the economics of the performing arts
    - Frank E. Seidman Award, 1982 (Box 59)
      Includes files from service on award selection committee
    - Free-Market Economies Conference, 2003; 4 folders (Box 64)
      Includes materials for conference organizing and follow-up publications
    - Future of the Cost Disease, 1984 (Box 18)
      Includes materials for conference presentation on the cost disease and performing arts in Nice, France
    - Germany Trip, 2006 (Box 64)
      Includes materials for conference on entrepreneurship and growth
    - Groupe de Recherce en Economie de la Culture, undated (Box 18)
      Includes files for research group in cultural economics
    - Growth in Inequality, Unemployment Duration and Related Problems, 1997-1998; 2 folders (Box 27)
      Includes draft research proposal to the Taub Foundation
    - Growth Machine, undated (Box 64)
    - Growth Policy and the Services, 1983 (Box 64)
      Includes materials for conference at Wharton
    - Guest Lectures, 1984-1986 (Box 59)
      Includes files for arranging various lectures
    - Healthcare and Human Services, 1993-1998 (Box 59)
      Includes files related to offering commentary on health care services to Daniel Patrick Moynihan
    - Hitachi, 1998-1999 (Box 27)
      Includes materials for Hitachi Foundation Global Corporate Citizenship Initiative
    - HOPE Conference, 2008 (Box 64)
      Includes correspondence related to conference hosted by History of Political Economy journal
    - Humphrey Institute, 2006 (Box 64)
    - Industry Consulting: General Foods, 1963 (Box 83)
      Includes files for consulting on optimal advertising expenditures
    - Institute for Defense Analyses, 1964 (Box 64)
      Includes materials related to consulting agreement
    - Interaction between Price Changes and Government Regulations, 1977 (Box 40)
      Includes draft research proposal
    - International Convergence of Productivity, 1992 (Box 40)
      Includes materials for conference planning
    - International Research and Exchanges Board, 1983 (Box 64)
      Includes materials for visits by international scholars
    - Interschool humanities council, 1976 (Box 64)
    - Japan and the World Economy, 1987 (Box 40)
      Includes correspondence related to establishing the journal
    - Joint Council on Economic Education (JCEE), 1990 (Box 40)
      Includes materials related to report on education and economics
    - Joint Council on Economic Education (JCEE), undated (Box 15)
      Includes files related to fellowship program funded by the Council
    - JCEE/Exxon Education Project, 1986 (Box 27)
      Includes research proposal on inequality in education for the Joint Council on Economic Education and the Exxon Education Foundation
    - Kauffman Foundation, 2004-2010; 6 folders (Box 64)
      Includes materials for grants for research on entrepreneurship
    - Kauffman Founation - KACE 2005, 2002-2005; 36 document (PDF format), audiovisual, and still image (JPEG format) files; approximately 117 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-OP-0002)
      Includes files for a conference on teaching with case studies.
    - Knowledge Sector Research Proposal, 1985 (Box 40)
      Research proposal for Institute for Research on Public Policy
    - Leontief Award, 1978 (Box 64)
      Includes files for service on the award selection committee
    - Levy Institute, 1995-1999 (Box 64)
    - Library of Congress, 1976-1977 (Box 15)
      Includes materials for report on production and dissemination of knowledge
    - Limiting Market Power: Regulation of Industry Proposal, 1988 (Box 65)
      Includes grant proposal to the Russell Sage Foundation
    - Lionel Robbins Memorial Fund, 1983-1986 (Box 59)
      Includes files related to serving on board
    - Localtel, 1992-1994; 2 folders (Box 59)
      Includes files for consulting on local telephone service
    - MacArthur, 1998-1999 (Box 27)
      Includes materials on MacArthur Foundation activities
    - Mathematica, Inc., 1975 (Box 64)
    - McCarter Theatre, 1979-1980 (Box 64)
      Includes files related to service as a trustee
    - Media Selection, 1963 (Box 15)
      Includes consulting report on computers and media
    - Mellon Foundation, 1996-1998 (Box 65)
      Includes research report for grant-funded project on Puerto Rico
    - Misc. Proposals, 1960-1965 (Box 15)
      Includes proposal on developing an objective function for the National Biscuit Program
    - Miscellaneous Talks, undated; 3 folders (Box 64)
      Includes presentation materials for various unsorted talks given by Baumol
    - Monsanto, 1957 (Box 15)
      Includes materials for consulting on inventory analysis
    - Morgan Stanley, 1963-1964 (Box 15)
      Includes materials for consulting pricing of convertible securities
    - National Academy of Sciences, 1982-1990; 4 folders (Box 15)
      Includes materials for project on development of science and technology, service on committee on the relationship between universities and the government, and service on site evaluation committee for a supercollider funded by the Department of Energy
    - National Institute of Economics and Law, 1984 (Box 15)
      Includes materials related to serving on board of advisors
    - National Science Foundation (NSF), 2006 (Box 64)
      Includes materials on research funded by the foundation
    - NSF, 1987-1989; 2 folders (Box 59)
      Includes files for various projects on productivity, Puerto Rico, and comparative economic development
    - NSF: Amendment, 1981 (Box 65)
      Includes files lobbying against proposed reductions in NSF funding
    - NSF: Fritz Machlup, 1982-1983; 3 folders (Box 59)
      Includes files for project on production and dissemination of knowledge initially granted to Fritz Machlup and completed by Baumol
    - NSF: Letters on behalf of Nihat Sargin, 1988 (Box 15)
      Includes letters advocating on behalf of a political prisoner
    - NSF: Market Mechanism and Technology Transfer, 1989 (Box 65)
      Includes research report for grant-funded project
    - NSF: Productivity Grant at NYU, 1990 (Box 59)
      Includes files for study on productivity growth and economic development
    - NSF: Proposal, 2007 (Box 40)
      Includes drafts of proposal on entrepreneurship and US competitiveness
    - NSF: Proposals referee reports, 1976-1979 (Box 65)
      Includes files for refereeing proposals
    - NSF: Proposals Reviewed, 1981-1989; 2 folders (Box 15)
      Includes proposals refereed by Baumol
    - NSF: R and D, Productivity Growth, and Asymptotically Stagnant Activities, 1985 (Box 40)
      Includes research proposal
    - NSF: Scale Economies and Public Attributes of Information, 1974-1977; 5 folders (Box 66)
      Includes draft project reports, grant proposals, and other related materials
    - NSF: Science and Tech Centers Review Panel, 1990 (Box 59)
      Includes files for proposed research center
    - NSF: Toward a theory of determination of Market Form, 1977-1980 (Box 66)
    - Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD), 1980-1981 (Box 66)
      Includes materials for commentary on organization reports
    - OECD Futures Project, 1980-1981 (Box 65)
      Includes research reports for the OECD
    - P. Ballantine and Sons, 1963 (Box 66)
      Includes consulting report on advertising
    - Patent Talks, undated (Box 65)
    - Pew Grant, 1989; 2 folders (Box 27)
      Includes proposal and final report for research project on faculty development and a program on economic education for the Pew Charitable Trusts
    - Pew Scholars Seminar, 1987-1988 (Box 22)
      Includes materials for seminar sponsored by the Pew Trust
    - Pew Trust Materials, 1984-1989; 9 folders (Box 22)
      Includes grant proposals, final reports, and related materials for project on economic education
    - Pfizer Grant, 1980-1981 (Box 66)
      Includes materials related to grant-funded project on futures markets
    - Philadelphia Retail, 1960 (Box 66)
      Includes materials for consulting on retail competition
    - Presidential address to the Atlantic Economic Society and expert testimony, 1983-1986; 9 text files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0104)
    - Price Caps for ECPR Talks, 2005 (Box 65)
      Includes materials for talk given at Fair Trade Commission
    - Price Caps Petroleum Policy, undated (Box 65)
    - Price Grant, 1990-1991; 2 folders (Box 22)
      Includes materials for grant-funded project on Entrepreneurship and the Dissemination of Prosperity funded by the Price Institute
    - Privatization and ECPR, 1995 (Box 65)
      Includes lecture notes
    - Proposal on Patent System, undated (Box 65)
      Includes draft proposal to study patent systems
    - Proposals, 1994-1996 (Box 22)
      Includes unsorted proposals and related materials
    - Proposals for a Program to Facilitate the Transfer of Foreign Technology to the US, 1992 (Box 40)
      Includes draft proposal sent to Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan
    - Public Interest Economics Foundation, 1984 (Box 66)
      Includes materials related to foundation ceasing operations
    - Puerto Rico-Mainland Center for Applied Economic Research, 1990 (Box 65)
      Includes draft proposal for a research center
    - Qualcomm, 2005 (Box 65)
      Includes draft consulting report on regulation of the wireless spectrum
    - Reser - Tampere, Finland, 2006 (Box 65)
      Includes lecture on prices and terrorism
    - Report and comments on price controls for medical services, 1980; 4 text files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0061)
    - Resources for the Future, 1979-1982 (Box 66)
      Includes materials related to service on the Research Advisory Committee and a grant-funded project
    - Robbins Chicago Session, undated (Box 65)
      Includes lecture notes on the work of Lionel Robbins
    - Rockefeller Foundation, 2010 (Box 65)
      Includes materials for conference on health care hosted by the foundation
    - Russell Sage Preliminary Grant, 1997 (Box 22)
      Includes materials for grant proposal for project on Downsizing and Some Possible Consequences for Employment, Inequality and Profits
    - Senator D.P. Moynihan, 1993-1996; 2 folders (Box 22)
      Includes materials for consulting on health care legislation issues
    - Smith-Richardson Foundation, 2004-2007 (Box 65)
      Includes materials for draft proposal
    - Southern Railway, 1963-1965 (Box 66)
      Includes materials for consulting on cost structures and pricing
    - Stockholm Conference, 2007 (Box 65)
      Includes conference booklet from conference on Swedish innovations
    - Swedish Inventors Council, undated (Box 65)
      Includes presentation materials for a talk on small businesses in Sweden
    - Symposium in Honor of Herbert Giersch, 2006 (Box 65)
      Includes conference booklet
    - Talk on Cournot and Collusion, 2000 (Box 65)
    - Talk on Globalization, undated (Box 65)
      Includes materials for presentation at unknown location
    - Talk on Innovation, 2003 (Box 65)
    - Talk on Patents as Dissemination Aid, 2005 (Box 65)
    - Talk on Regulation Misled by Perfect Competition Model, 2005 (Box 65)
      Includes lecture notes for presentation at unknown location
    - Talk on the Unmatched Economic Development of the Past Two Centuries, 2005 (Box 65)
    - Talk Outline, undated; 2 folders (Box 17)
      Includes unsorted notes for various talks given by Baumol
    - Talks in Progress, 2003-2005 (Box 65)
      Includes draft materials for presentations
    - Talks on Entrepreneurship and Innovation, undated (Box 65)
      Includes unsorted materials for various presentations
    - Telecommunications, 1995-1997 (Box 22)
      Includes materials for consulting on deregulation in telecommunications
    - Theatres Communications Group, undated (Box 18)
      Includes files related to membership and data from the group
    - Twentieth Century Fund, 1983 (Box 66)
      Includes draft proposal for project on anti-protectionist policies
    - US-Japan Possible Study, 1986 (Box 40)
      Research proposal on comparative historical growth process in the US and Japan
    - Wharton School of Finance and Commerce, 1960 (Box 66)
      Includes materials for advising on an applied economic program
    - World Resources Institute, 1982-1988; 3 folders (Box 22)
      Includes materials related to serving on the board and council, and participating in institute conferences
  - Engagements, 1981-2007; 2
    Includes files on Baumol's various speaking engagements.
    - Engagements, 1981-1984; 3 folders (Box 65)
      Includes correspondence related to speaking engagements, conferences, and other professional activities
    - Engagements, 1982-2007 (Box 59)
    - Engagements - Accepted/Pending, 1985-1990; 9 folders (Box 11)
    - Engagements - Not Accepted, 1984 (Box 59)
      Includes correspondence related to declined speaking engagements
    - Engagements - Not Accepted, 1984-1990; 6 folders (Box 11)
    - Pending Engagements, 2006-2007; 2 folders (Box 59)
      Includes files and correspondence for engagements currently underway
    - Sample Regrets Letter, 1986 (Box 11)
      Includes template letter declining invitation
  - Legal Testimony, 1958-2006 and undated; 3
    This subseries includes files on testimonies given by Baumol in various settings. These include testimony as an expert witness in many legal cases concerning regulating/deregulating particular corporations and industries, and testimony before houses of the U.S. Congress and U.S. government regulatory agencies.
    - Air Passenger Computer Reservations Systems Antitrust Litigation, 1989-1990; 6 folders (Box 66)
    - Atlantic Richfield co. v. State of Alaska, 1983 (Box 83)
      Includes expert witness testimony related to Alaska oil pipeline
    - ATT, 1993 (Box 40)
    - ATT Communications of California, undated (Box 75)
    - ATT Communications of New York, 1987 (Box 75)
    - ATT Testimony, undated (Box 66)
    - ATT testimony, 1990; 2 text files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0033)
    - Baumol Testimony Lists, 2003; 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Bell Atlantic and NYNEX v. ATT, 1994; 3 folders (Box 21)
    - Bell Testimony, 1970 (Box 21)
    - Cases of Charges being put into practice or being objected to, 1976-1977 (Box 21)
    - Chlorine and Caustic Soda Antitrust Litigation, 1987 (Box 21)
    - City of New York, v. United States Department of Commerce, 1989 (Box 21)
    - Civil Aeronautics Board, 1983 (Box 21)
    - Coal Rate Litigation, 1984 (Box 21)
    - Coal Trading Co. et al. v the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad, 1987; 2 text files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0059)
    - Computer Inquiry Project, 1984-1985; 3 folders (Box 75)
      Includes materials related to testimony on world competition in telecommunications
    - Consolidated Rail Corporation, 1993 (Box 21)
    - Copyright Royalty Tribunal, undated (Box 75)
    - CSX Transportation Inc./Dayton Power and Light Company Coal Rate Litigation, 1990 (Box 21)
    - Federal Communications Commission: ATT, 1966-1976; 16 folders (Box 69)
      Includes materials for Baumol's testimony related to regulation of ATT
    - Federal Communications Commission: ATT, 1975-1995; 18 folders (Box 70)
    - Federal Communications Commission: Testimony, 1983-1988; 58 document and text files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0051)
    - Federal Trade Commission: BAT Industries and Appleton Papers, 1982; 3 folders (Box 71)
    - Federal Trade Commission: Coca-Cola Company, 1986 (Box 71)
    - Federal Trade Commission: Echlin Manufacturing Co. and Borg-Warner Corp., 1985 (Box 71)
    - Fidelity Management and Research Co. and Brokerage Commission Rates, 1985; undated (Box 21)
    - Fidelity Management and Research Co. and Brokerage Rates, 1985; undated (Box 83)
    - Files for testimony on antitrust regulation, 1989; 10 text files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0036)
    - Files on deregulation in telecommunications industry, 1983-1986; 9 text files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0108)
    - Government: Committee on Appropriations, 1982 (Box 75)
      Printed volume of hearings related to Department of Housing and Urban Development
    - Government: Committee on the Judiciary, 1981 (Box 75)
      Printed volume of hearings on competition in telecommunications
    - Government: Joint Economic Committee, 1958 (Box 21)
    - Government: National Science Foundation Budget, 1982 (Box 21)
      Includes files related to testimony in favor of restoring the NSF budget for social sciences research
    - Government: Senate Judiciary Committee, 1981 (Box 21)
    - Government: Senate Public Works Committee on Materials Policy, 1976 (Box 21)
    - Government: Senate Subcommittee on Employment and Productivity, 1982 (Box 21)
    - Government: State of New York Assembly, 1984 (Box 21)
    - Government: Subcommittee on Activities of Regulatory Agencies Relating to Small Business, 1968 (Box 21)
    - Government: Subcommittee on Telecommunications, Consumer Protection, and Finance, 1981 (Box 75)
      Printed volume of hearings on deregulation in telecommunications
    - Government: Telecommunications Bill, 1982 (Box 21)
    - Government: US House of Representatives, 1981-1982; undated (Box 21)
    - Grand Metropolitan PLC, 1988 (Box 21)
    - Interstate Commerce Commission: Railroad Pricing and Revenue Adequacy, 1970-1983; 12 folders (Box 71)
      Includes materials for Baumol's testimony on railroad rate regulations
    - Interstate Commerce Commission: Railroad Pricing and Revenue Adequacy, 1983; 10 folders (Box 72)
    - Interstate Commerce Commission: Railroad Pricing and Revenue Adequacy, 1984-1986; 15 folders (Box 73)
    - Interstate Commerce Commission: Railroad Pricing and Revenue Adequacy, 1980s-1994; 13 folders (Box 74)
    - Legal Consulting, 1982-1996; 12 folders (Box 67)
      Includes materials for various minor expert witness testimony engagements
    - Louisville and Nashville R.R. v. United States, 1967 (Box 67)
    - Low Density Polyethylene Resins Antitrust Litigation, 1982-1984; 2 folders (Box 67)
    - Lower Lake Erie Iron Ore Antitrust Litigation, 1989; 2 folders (Box 67)
    - Materials on regulation of ATT, 1989; 5 text files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0038)
    - MCI Communications Corp. v. ATT, 1977; 2 folders (Box 67)
    - Merger Guidelines, 1984 (Box 75)
      Includes materials related to Department of Justice antitrust merger guidelines
    - Midtec v. CNW, 1986 (Box 67)
    - Miscellaneous Testimony and Papers, undated; 4 folders (Box 75)
      Includes materials for various testimonies given and related resources
    - New England Telephone and Telegraph Company, undated; 2 folders (Box 75)
    - New Zealand Telecom, 1992 (Box 75)
    - Polaroid v Kodak, 1988 (Box 22)
      Includes consulting report and presentation materials commenting on legal proceeding
    - Polaroid v Kodak, 1989; 11 document and text files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0034)
      Files related to expert testimony
    - Polaroid v Kodak, 1989; 5 text files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0035)
      Files related to expert testimony.
    - Postal Rate Commission, 1973-1990; 2 folders (Box 41)
    - Public Utilities, 1985-1994; undated; 17 folders (Box 41)
      Includes documents related to legal testimony concerning public utilities in California, Illinois, Maine, Missouri, New Jersey, New York, Ohio, Texas, Virginia, and Wisconsin
    - Railroad Accounting Principles Board, 1986-1987; 2 folders (Box 75)
    - Sharon Steel Corporation, 1981 (Box 68)
    - Tax Court: G.D. Searle, 1982 (Box 68)
    - Tax Court: Perkin-Elmer Corporation, 1991 (Box 68)
    - Tax Court: Sundstrand Corp., 1987 (Box 68)
    - TCA Building Co. v. Northwestern Resources Co., 1984; 2 folders (Box 68)
    - Testimony, 1996-2006 (Box 68)
      Includes unsorted documents related to testimony
    - Transcript Corrections, undated (Box 40)
      Includes corrections made to an unlabeled testimony
    - U.S. Dept. of Energy v. Baltimore and Ohio Railroad Co., 1991 (Box 68)
    - U.S. Wats v. ATT, 1995 (Box 68)
    - U.S.A. v. AMR Corporation, 2000; undated; 2 folders (Box 68)
    - United Airlines Case Testimony, 1988; 2 text files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0060)